Guide to the ILGWU Records, 1884-2006, bulk 1923-1995.
ILGWU Records, 1884-2006, bulk 1923-1995.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives
ILGWU Records, 1884-2006, bulk 1923-1995.
5780
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.
2,527 linear feet.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Martin P. Catherwood Library, Cornell University
Archives of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU) which document the history of the most significant labor union representing workers in the women's garment industry in the United States and Canada.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The ILGWU was formed on June 3, 1900, by eleven delegates representing local unions in New York, Philadelphia, Baltimore, and Newark. These local unions—the United Brotherhood of Cloak Makers, the Skirt Makers Union No. 1 of Greater New York, the Cloak Makers’ Protective Union of Philadelphia, the Cloak Makers Union of Baltimore, the Cloak Makers’ Union of Brownsville, and the Cloak Makers’ Union of Newark, New Jersey—were comprised primarily of Jewish immigrants who had recently arrived from Eastern Europe, many of whom were socialist and had been active trade unionists before coming to America, and in some instances, had become members of the ILGWU’s predecessor unions upon arrival. The ILGWU was granted a charter from the American Federation of Labor on June 22, 1900.
The ILGWU was an important force in establishing the rights to unionize, bargain collectively, and work under safe conditions. In the opening decade of the twentieth century, galvanizing events such as the “Uprising of the 20,000” (1909-1910), the “Great Revolt” (1910), and the Protocol of Peace (1910) helped the union grow quickly and push for major workplaces changes in the industry. A fire at the Triangle Shirtwaist Factory on March 25, 1911, claimed the lives of 146 young women and men and spurred cooperation between organized labor, government, and social reformers to institute unprecedented workplace inspection and regulation.
At the same time, and especially as the union grew, the union’s agenda was not limited strictly to workplace issues. The ILGWU developed several elements of “social unionism.” In addition to maintaining Health, Welfare, and Vacation Funds for members, many local unions also organized Education Departments that presented a variety of course offerings to members, ranging from English language classes, to labor history classes, to visual and performing arts classes. The ILGWU’s Union Health Center in New York City was established in 1913 and chartered in 1930, and Union Health Centers and Mobile Health Units in other locations were soon founded elsewhere; the staff at these centers provided consultation and health services to union members across the United States. The union’s cooperative housing complexes offered affordable options for workers in New York City, and the ILGWU’s Unity House, a resort in the Pocono Mountains of Pennsylvania established in 1919 (and closed in 1989), served as a relatively inexpensive getaway for union members and their families. By the time David Dubinsky was elected president of the ILGWU, the union’s many and varied programs were large and robust, and the union was a formidable presence in American organized labor.
During David Dubinsky’s tenure as president of the ILGWU from 1932 to 1966, the ILGWU grew in numbers, influence, and ambition. As more garment workers in New York City joined the union, manufacturers sought to establish shops where they could hire non-unionized workers and thus turn a greater profit. When these “runaway” shops opened up New England, central Pennsylvania, and the Southeastern United States, the ILGWU followed. The union sent organizers to newly-opened shops, and eventually established district councils and regional departments to gain members and represent these “out-of-town” workers. During this time, the ILGWU established its Training Institute to prepare students for organizing and staff positions with the growing union.
With an increasingly large membership, the union had become even more involved in cultural and educational activities. The musical “Pins and Needles” opened at New York City’s Labor Stage in 1937 and enjoyed a successful Broadway run until 1940; in 1950, the Northeast Department musical narrative, “My Name Is Mary Brown,” was staged at the ILGWU Golden Jubilee Convention in Atlantic City; the ILGWU-produced feature film “With These Hands,” too, was premiered at that convention, and it was later released nationwide. The ILGWU Chorus and local unions’ mandolin orchestras continued to perform at union events in their local communities.
Meanwhile, the ILGWU was becoming increasingly involved in domestic partisan politics and international affairs. The ILGWU became a key stakeholder and major financial contributor to the American Labor Party and later the Liberal Party of New York, before finally aligning with the Democratic Party in the 1960s. By 1962, John F. Kennedy was on hand to ceremoniously open the ILGWU’s cooperative housing at Penn Station South, and in 1964, Lyndon B. Johnson gave a speech to observe the 50th anniversary of the Union Health Center’s opening. In addition, the ILGWU’s Legislative and Political Department, under the longtime direction of Evelyn Dubrow, participated in many and legislative and electoral efforts, with local unions also coordinating activities on the municipal and state levels. A wide range of ILGWU officers presented testimony on a variety of topics relating to trade, workplace conditions, and other labor issues before the U.S. Congress.
On the international scene, in the years leading up to the United States’ involvement in World War II, the ILGWU collaborated with other labor organizations, such as the Jewish Labor Committee and the Italian-American Labor Council, to oppose the rise of fascism and Hitler in Europe; and in the post-war period, under David Dubinsky’s intensely anti-communist leadership, the ILGWU worked closely with AFL leadership to provide material aid to those in war-ravaged Europe and establish non-Communist unions in the region in decolonizing countries.
Nevertheless, over the course of its history, the ILGWU’s international leadership was consistently criticized as non-representative of the union membership. In the union’s early years, this disparity was primarily gendered; a disproportionate number of men rose from the powerful local unions in New York City to hold office of a union whose membership was overwhelmingly female. As the racial demographics of the union changed, especially in the post-war period, the relative absence of union leaders who had risen from the ranks of more recent immigrant members earned the union critics, among them the NAACP. The ILGWU’s reputation as a progressive force in American organized labor was further tarnished by the divisive issue of the right of union staff to organize. Though clerical workers of the ILGWU were organized as part of the Office Employees International Union (OEIU), the ILGWU, and especially David Dubinsky, came under criticism for the treatment of union staff who sought to organize themselves, namely the Federation of Union Representatives (FOUR).
In the 1970s and 1980s, the decline of the United States garment manufacturing industry accelerated. Efforts to stem this decline included the ILGWU’s aggressive campaign to educate American consumers of the importance of buying products bearing the Union Label, testimony before Congressional committees on the effects of imports on garment workers in the United States, and increased collaboration with international federations of clothing workers unions. These conditions, compounded by the controversial issue of regulating homework, posed serious challenges to the union. One response was designed and executed at the local union level, and then expanded for the national membership; from 1983 to 1995, the Immigration Project represented and advised individuals on immigration, naturalization, and amnesty matters, the first such program of this kind established by an American union. Another response was to engage and help in the growth of workers’ centers in the United States and more actively engage with organizing efforts outside of the United States.
By the mid-1990s, however, the strategy for responding to the United States’ declining women’s garment manufacturing industry was to merge with the union that had represented workers in the men’s garment manufacturing industry, the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU). At a joint convention in 1995, the two unions merged to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). Now under the leadership of President Jay Mazur, the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
SCOPE AND CONTENT NOTE
The ILGWU Records include substantial historical documentation from many of International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union's key officers, central offices, regional units, joint boards and local unions. In addition to correspondence, minutes, and publications, the ILGWU archives contains union and garment industry work artifacts and memorabilia, audio-visual materials and a substantial series of historical photographs. See Series Descriptions for more information.
ARRANGEMENT
Series I. Constitutions, By-Laws and Conventions, 1893-1995
Series II. Joint Boards, District Councils and Regional Departments, 1901-2000
Series III. Locals, 1901-1996
Series IV. Officers and Staff, 1911-2006
Series V. General Executive Board, 1900-1995
Series VI. Contracts and Case Files, 1907-2000
Series VII. Departments and Institutions, 1884-1999
Series VIII. Printed Material, 1910-1995
Series IX. Audio-Visual, 1885-1995
Series X. Scrapbooks and Memorabilia, 1910-1995
Series XI. Miscellany, 1985-1992
SERIES DESCRIPTIONS
SERIES I. CONSTITUTIONS, BY-LAWS AND CONVENTIONS, 1893-1995
Taken together, the four collections that constitute Series I, Constitutions, By-Laws and Conventions, 1893-1995, document the founding of the ILGWU and the structure of its governance through 1995 when it merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union to form UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). This series includes the ILGWU’s constitutions and bylaws from 1903 to 1992, as well as constitutions and bylaws for units comprising the ILGWU such as local unions, local unions’ health and welfare funds, and joint boards. Constitutions and bylaws are complemented by documentation of the ILGWU’s conventions held between 1900 and 1995. This documentation includes published reports of proceedings, and for some of the conventions, partial transcription of proceedings, notes, and ephemera.
While these four collections are the foundation of documentation on this aspect of the ILGWU, other parts of the ILGWU Records complement them. Materials in Series VII, Printed Material, offer published reports on the International’s conventions. Collection 5780 PUBS, Publications, includes off-prints of reports to delegates at the ILGWU conventions, as well as other printed material published on the occasion of the international convention, such as ILGWU News-History, 1900-1950. Issues of the ILGWU’s official organs—The Ladies’ Garment Worker, Justice, Giustizia, Justicia, and Gerechtigkeit—as well as the publications of local unions, joint boards, district councils, and regional departments also report on the union’s conventions.
In addition to these publications, portions of the records of local unions, district councils and regional departments, as well as the papers of ILGWU presidents, other officers, and staff complement the convention records in this series. Dispersed throughout the records of local unions, district councils, and regional departments are draft resolutions, correspondence, memoranda, and other materials relating to the selection of delegates to the international convention. The presidential papers of Benjamin Schlesinger, Morris Sigman, David Dubinsky, Louis Stulberg, Sol Chaikin, and Jay Mazur include correspondence and memoranda, presidential remarks, and printed material related to ILGWU conventions. The papers of Assistants to the President—Wilbur Daniels, James Lipsig, and Carl Proper—include off-prints of committee and department reports to the delegates, administrative files and notes, and other materials pertaining to conventions. The papers of Irwin Solomon, General Secretary-Treasurer of the ILGWU at the time of its merger with ACTWU, are noteworthy for their documentation of the work leading up to the creation of UNITE in 1995, in addition to records of earlier conventions.
Complementary to the text collections of the ILGWU Records, there are photographs, film, video, audio, and ephemera that document the ILGWU’s conventions. Collections 5780 AV, Audio-Visual, and 5780 F contain film, video, and audio recordings documenting some ILGWU conventions between 1950 and 1995. These recordings include speeches, reports, performances, and presentation and discussion of resolutions. Collection 5780 P, Photographs, contains many images of the ILGWU’s conventions; these include group photographs of members and delegates, staff and officers, the General Executive Board and committees, as well as of all the attendees in the large venues where the conventions were held. Collection 5780 MB, Memorabilia, includes ephemera distributed in conjunction with the ILGWU’s convention such as medals, ribbons, badges, and pins; scarves, hats, and pendants; and pens and fans.
SERIES II. JOINT BOARDS, DISTRICT COUNCILS AND REGIONAL DEPARMENTS, 1901-2000
Series II contains the records of several ILGWU joint boards, district councils, and regional departments throughout the United States and Canada. This series is divided into two subseries: Subseries A. Joint Boards; and Subseries B. District Councils and Regional Departments.
The scope and content and physical disarray or records contained in this series vary considerably. The records for some joint boards, district councils, and regional departments are far more extensive than others, and many joint boards, district councils, and regional departments of the ILGWU are not represented at all. In some instances, the records of a joint board, district council, or regional department also contain files of, or pertaining to, constitutive local unions, such as meeting minutes, election results, and correspondence.
Subseries A, Joint Boards, 1909-1981
The charter and jurisdiction of Joint Boards was of perennial interest to the ILGWU, though the requirements for charter and the jurisdictional scope of the organizations changed over time. According to the International’s 1918 constitution, “Two or more L.U.s located in the same city or locality and engaged in various branches of the same trade shall organize a joint board. All the branches engaged in the manufacture of cloaks, suits, reefers, and skirts, shall be considered one trade.” In the years to follow, the branches considered to be part of one trade were not outlined in the constitution, but left to the discretion of the General Executive Board. By 1992, the requirements for chartering a joint board became even more flexible, providing that “Two or more locals located in the same city or locality may organize a joint board, if granted a charter by the GEB, which shall define the powers and jurisdiction of such joint board.” Even while the requirements for chartering a joint board (and joint council) changed somewhat throughout the ILGWU’s existence, the primary purpose of the joint board remained consistent—to negotiate agreements, settle grievances between members and employers, monitor conditions in union shops, and manage union staff and funds, and if necessary, discipline members found guilty of misconduct.
In this subseries, joint boards in eight cities—Boston, Chicago, Cleveland, Los Angeles, Montreal, New York City, San Francisco, and Toronto—are documented in 21 unique collections. These collections are arranged alphabetically by state or province, and within state or province, alphabetically by city.
The records of joint boards in New York City, spanning from 1913 to 1977, comprise the bulk of this subseries, and consist of a wide range of material. Included are meeting minutes of the board, memoranda pertaining to the joint board’s operation, materials generated through the grievance process, as well as correspondence with the board’s constitutive local unions and departments of the international. Also of note are records documenting the ILGWU’s participation in New York State Governor Alfred Smith’s Advisory Commission on the Cloak, Suit, and Skirt Industry beginning in 1924.
While the bulk of records in this subseries document the work of joint boards in New York, there are significant holdings of records of Joint Boards in Boston, Chicago, Cleveland, Los Angeles, Montreal, San Francisco, and Toronto. The largest of these collections are the records of the Montreal Joint Board. These include correspondence with members, local unions, and the international office, as well as reports and meeting minutes, conference files, materials relating to the board’s work in negotiations, elections, and the Quebec Federation of Labor. Some materials of the Montreal Joint Council, as well as extensive materials pertaining to local unions in Quebec are also included; joint councils were composed of joint boards and other affiliates. The records of the Chicago Joint Board contains similar materials relating to that affiliate’s work in that city, as well as correspondence with joint boards in other parts of the country. The records of the Los Angeles Joint Board are the only text collection in this subseries with a complementary photograph collection; these photographs, contained in Collection 5780/046 P, show members in Los Angeles participating in meetings, conventions, officer installations, parades, and other events.
In addition to documenting the activities of the ILGWU’s joint boards, the collections comprising this subseries also offer evidence of the work of local unions in their city or locality. This record sometimes consists of correspondence with members of those local unions about their activities or grievances; other times, meeting minutes forwarded from the local unions are the full extent of the records that the joint board maintained. Thus, researchers interested in the work of a particular local union should review records in this subseries, as well as records in Series III., Local Unions, 1901-1996.
Subseries B, District Councils and Regional Departments, 1901-2000
District Councils were constituted of local unions that were not part of a joint board, with the primary purpose of organizing garment workers in their area. In addition to organizing the workers of their area, these affiliates were bound by rights and duties as determined by the General Executive Board; when no determination was made, district councils enjoyed the same provisions as did the joint boards. Regional departments of the ILGWU, such as the Cloak-Out-of-Town Department or the Upper South Department, likewise were composed of local unions that were not part of a joint board; however, regional departments might be constituted of both local unions and district councils (e.g., the Southeast Region was composed of dozens of local unions, plus the North Carolina District Council, which was composed of ten local unions).
This subseries is constituted of 19 collections, arranged alphabetically by name of district council or regional department. This subseries contains records of several Pennsylvania district councils, as well as records of the Pacific Northwest District Council, Western Massachusetts District Council, and some files of Canadian joint councils. This subseries also contains records of the following regional department: Midwest, Northeast, Ohio Kentucky, Southeast, Upper South, and Western States.
A portion of several collections in this subseries contain the papers of several officers and staff. The papers of David Gingold, longtime director of the Northeast Department, are contained in that department’s records. In the records of the Pacific Northwest District Council, there are correspondence and notes of manager Mattie Jackson and her successor, Katie Quan. The largest collection in this subseries, Western States Region Records, contain papers of several staff members between 1940 and 1985: Cornelius Wall, Max Wolf, Ralph Smith, and Meyer Silverstein. Other strengths of this subseries included regular reports from organizers in the Southeast Region Department, records documenting the work of the Northeastern Pennsylvania Stakeholder Alliance relating to the closure of Leslie Fay facilities in that region, and collective bargaining agreements negotiated by the Mid-West Region Department. This subseries is rounded out by issues of The Garment Worker and Ohio Kenucky News, publications of the Central Pennsylvania District Council and the Ohio Kentucky Region, respectively; researchers interested in publications of district councils and regional departments of the ILGWU should also consult the finding aid for 5780 PUBS, ILGWU Publications.
The photograph and audio-visual collections in this subseries document the operations of the affiliates, such as meetings and conferences, strikes and rallies, and classes and recreational outings. The Central Pennsylvania District photographs are the largest of the two photograph collections, and they show the diversity of activities of the district’s members. The audio-visual materials include films and videos that were either created or produced by the affiliates, or that featured the affiliates, their members, or officers of the ILGWU. Collection 5780/038 AV, Canadian Area films, appears to include many dozens of reels of audio and film that were created in the course of producing Les Midinettes.
As does Subseries A, the collections comprising this subseries also offer record of the work of local unions in their city or locality. This record sometimes consists of correspondence with members of those local unions about their activities or grievances; other times, meeting minutes forwarded from the local unions are the full extent of the records that the joint board maintained. Thus, researchers interested in the work of a particular local union should review records in this subseries, as well as records in Series III., Local Unions, 1901-1996.
SERIES III. LOCALS, 1901-1996
Over the course of the ILGWU’s existence, dozens of local unions came into and out of existence. Many were formed, then dissolved or merged with other unions, as membership ballooned with the growth of the organized ladies’ garment industry in the United States and diminished with its decline. In 1900, the ILGWU charted four local unions—the Cloak Makers’ Union of New York Local Union 1; the Cloak Makers’ Union Protective Union of Philadelphia Local Union 2; the United Cloak Pressers of Philadelphia Local 3; and the Cloak Makers’ Union of Baltimore Local Union 4. In 1994, the year before the ILGWU’s merger with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers to create UNITE, over 200 local unions were included in the International’s joint boards, district councils, and departments.
While the rules governing the composition, rights, and responsibilities of local unions changed somewhat between 1900 and 1995, the requirement for chartering a local union largely remained consistent: Local unions were composed of at least seven workers in the same branch of the garment industry who applied for and received a charter by the General Executive Board of the ILGWU, and the local union could dissolve or join a non-ILGWU union only if, by a vote, fewer than seven members wished to retain the charter from the ILGWU.